So, let me use the mic to introduce Alex Townsend,
who taught here at MIT, taught linear algebra 1806, very successfully.
And now he's at Cornell on the faculty, still teaching very successfully.
And he was invited here yesterday for a big event over in engineering.
And he agreed to give a talk about a section of the book, section 4.3,
which, if you look at it, is a section of the book.
If you look at it, you'll see it's all about his work.
And now you get to hear from the creator himself.
Okay.
Should we pop that on?
Yeah.
Okay, thanks.
Thank you, Gil.
Thank you for inviting me here.
I hope you're enjoying the course.
Today, I want to tell you a little about why there are so many matrices that are low rank in the world.
So, as computational mathematicians, Gil and myself,
we come across matrices.
Low rank matrices all the time.
And we started wondering as a community, why?
What is it about the matrices, the problems that we're looking at?
What makes low rank matrices appear?
And today, I want to kind of give you that story, or at least an overview of that story.
So, for this class, X is going to be an n by n real matrix.
So, nice and simple.
Nice and square.
And you already know, or are very comfortable with, the singular values of a matrix.
So, the singular values of a matrix, as you know, are a sequence of numbers
that are monotonically non-increasing
that tell us all kinds of things about the matrix X.
For example, the number of...
The number of non-zero singular values tell us the rank of the matrix X.
And they also, you probably know, tell us how well a matrix X can be approximated by a low rank matrix.
So, let me just write two facts down that you already are familiar with.
So, here's a fact.
That if I look at the number of non-zero singular values in X,
so, I'm imagining there's going to be K non-zero singular values,
then we can say a few things about X.
For example, X, the rank of X, as we know, is K.
The number of non-zero singular values.
But we also know, from the SVD,
that we can decompose X into a sum of...
into a sum of...
of rank one matrices.
In fact, a sum of K of them.
So, because X is rank K,
we can write down a low rank representation for X,
and it involves K terms,
like this.
Each one of these vectors here is a column vector.
So, if I draw this pictorially,
this is a column vector.
This guy looks like this, right?
And we have K of them.
So, because X is rank K,
we can write X as a sum of K rank one matrices.
And we also have an initial fact that we already know,
that the dimension of the column space of X is equal to K.
And the same with the row space.
So, the col space of X equals the row space of X,
the dimension.
And that they all equal K.
So, there are three facts we can determine
from looking at this sequence of singular values
of a matrix X.
Of course, the singular value sequence is unique.
X defines that singular...
its own singular values.
Okay.
What we're interested in here is
what makes...
X...
what are the properties of X
that make sure that the singular values
have a lot of zeros in that sequence?
Can we try to understand
what kind of X makes that happen?
And we really like matrices
that have a lot of zeros here
for the following reason.
If X is...
we say X is low rank,
if the following holds, right?
Because we...
if we wanted to send X to our friend,
we're imagining X is a picture
where each entry is a pixel of that image.
If that matrix, that image, was low rank,
we could send the picture to our friend in two ways.
We could send one every single entry of X.
And for us to do that, we would have to send N squared.
Pieces of information,
because we'd have to send every entry.
But if X is sufficiently low rank,
we could also send then, our friend, the vectors.
U, U1, V1, UK up to VK.
And how many...
how much pieces of data would we have to send our friend
to get X to them if we sent in the low rank form?
Well, here there's two...
there's, um, 2N here, 2Y here,
2N here numbers.
There's K of them.
So we'd have to send 2KN numbers.
And we strictly say a matrix is low rank
if it's more efficient to send X to our friend
in low rank form than in full rank form.
Okay?
So this, of course, by a little calculation,
just shows us that,
provided the rank is less than half the size
of the matrix,
we are calling the matrix low rank.
Now, often in practice,
we demand more...
we demand that K is much smaller
than this number,
so that it's far more efficient
to send our friend the matrix X in low rank form
than in full rank form.
Okay?
So the colloquial use of the word low rank
is, uh, is kind of this situation.
But this is the strict definition of it.
Okay.
So what do, uh, low rank matrices look like?
And to do that, I have, uh, some pictures for you.
I have some flags, the world flags.
So these are all matrices X.
These examples, because they're flags,
happen to not be square.
Um, I hope you can all see this.
But what the top row here
are all matrices that are extremely low rank.
For example, the Austria flag,
if you want to send that to your friend,
that matrix is of rank one.
So all you have to do is send your friend two vectors.
You have to tell your friend the column space
and the row space.
And there's only...the dimensions are one of both.
For the English flag,
you need to send them two vectors.
So you have two column vectors,
uh, and two row vectors.
U1, V1, U2, and V2.
And as we go down this row,
they get slowly fuller and fuller rank.
So the Japanese flag, for example,
is low rank, but not, uh, not that small.
The Scottish flag is essentially full rank.
So it's very inefficient to send your friend
the Scottish flag, uh, in low rank form.
So you're sending almost every single entry.
So what do low rank matrices look like?
Well, if the matrix is extremely low rank,
like rank one,
then when you look at that matrix, like here,
like the flag, it's highly aligned
with the, uh, the coordinates,
with the rows and columns.
So if it's rank one,
the matrix is highly aligned,
like the Austria flag.
And of course, as we add in more and more rank here,
the situation gets a bit blurry.
For example, once we get into the medium rank situation,
which is a circle,
it's very hard to see that the circle is actually,
in fact, uh, low rank.
But what I wanted to do was try to understand
why the Scottish rank, the Scottish flag,
or diagonal patterns,
are particularly a bad example for low rank.
So I'm gonna take the triangular flag
to examine that more carefully.
So the triangular flag,
it looks like, I'll take a square,
and I'll take a square matrix,
and I'll color in the bottom half.
Okay, so this matrix is the matrix of ones
in below the diagonal.
Okay?
And I'm interested in this matrix,
and in particular its singular values,
to try to understand why diagonal patterns
are not particularly, uh, useful
for low rank, uh, compression.
And this, this matrix of all ones
has a really nice property that if I take its inverse,
it looks a lot like, uh,
getting close to Gil's favorite matrix.
So if I take the inverse of this matrix,
it has an inverse because it's got ones on the diagonal,
then its inverse...
is the following matrix,
which people familiar with finite difference schemes
will notice the familiarity between that
and the first order, uh, finite difference approximation.
Um, in particular, if I go a bit further
and times two of these together and do this,
then, uh, this is, uh, essentially Gil's favorite matrix.
Except one entry happens to be different.
Ends up being this matrix.
Okay?
Which is very close to the second order
central finite difference matrix.
And people have very well studied that matrix
and just know its, uh, eigenvalues,
its singular values.
They know everything about that matrix.
And you'll remember that if we know the eigenvalues
of the matrix,
we know the eigenvalues of a matrix
like X transpose X.
We know the singular values of X.
So this allows us to show
by the fact that we know that,
that the singular values
of this matrix, uh,
are not very amenable to low rank.
They're all non-zero.
And they don't even decay.
So, uh, I'm getting this from, uh,
I rang up Gil,
and Gil tells me these numbers.
That allows us to work out exactly what the singular values
of this matrix are from the connection to finite differences.
And so we can understand why this is not good
by looking at the singular values.
So the first singular value of X is,
from this expression,
is going to be, uh,
the value of X.
And that's going to be the value of X.
And that's going to be the value of Y.
And from this expression,
the last guy,
the last singular value of X,
is going to be approximately a half.
So these singular values are all large.
They're not getting close to zero.
If I plotted these singular values
on a graph,
right, so here's the first singular value,
the second singular value,
the third singular value,
the fourth singular value,
the fifth singular value,
all of these singular values,
all of these are going to be half.
And that's going to be,
the second and the nth,
then what would the graph look like?
Well, I'll plot these numbers.
I'll divide by this guy
so that they all are bounded
between 1 and 0
because of the normalization
because I divided by sigma 1 of x.
And so we can plot them
and they will look like
this kind of thing.
This number happens to be here
where they come to be pi over 4n,
which is me dividing this number
by this number approximately.
So triangular patterns
are extremely bad for low rank.
We need things,
or we at least intuitively think
that we need things
aligned with the rows and columns.
But the circle case
happens to also be low rank.
And so what happened
to the Japanese flag?
Why is the Japanese flag
convenient for low rank?
Well, it's the fact that it's a circle
and there's lots of symmetry in a circle.
So if I try to look at the rank
of a circle,
the Japanese flag,
then I can bound this rank
by decomposing the Japanese flag
into two things.
So this is going to be
less than or equal to
the rank of a sum of two matrices.
And I'll do it
so that the decomposition works out.
I have the circle.
I'm going to cut out
a rank one piece
that lives in the middle of this circle.
Okay.
And I'm going to cut out a square
from the interior of that circle.
Okay.
And I can figure out, of course,
the rank is just bounded
by the sum of those two ranks.
This guy is bounded by rank one
because it's highly aligned
with the grid.
Okay.
This is dark.
So this guy is bounded by rank one.
So this thing here
plus one.
And now I have to try to understand
the rank of this piece.
Now, this piece has lots of similarities.
This is the matrix of symmetry.
For example, we know that the rank of that matrix
is the dimension of the column space
and the dimension of the row space.
So when we look at this matrix,
because of symmetry,
if I divide this matrix in half along the columns,
all the columns on the left appear on the right.
So the columns, for example,
the rank of this matrix is the same as
the rank of that matrix,
because I didn't change the column space.
Okay.
Now I go again and divide along the rows.
And now the row dimension of this matrix
is the same as the top half,
because as I wipe out those,
I didn't change the dimension of the row space,
because the rows are the same top-bottom.
And so this becomes the rank
of that tiny little matrix there.
And because it's small,
it won't have too large a rank.
So this is definitely less than if I divide that up.
Little guy here, it looks like that.
Plus the other guy, it looks like that.
Plus one.
And so of course, the rows, the column,
the rows are the same.
Okay.
So the row space of this matrix
cannot be very high,
because this is a very thin matrix.
There's lots of zeros in that matrix,
only a few ones.
And so you can go along and do a bit of trig
to try to figure out
how many rows are non-zero in this matrix.
And a bit of trig tells you,
well, it depends on the radius of this original circle.
So if I make the original radius R
of this Japanese flag,
then the bound that you end up getting
will be for this matrix,
R one minus square root two over two
for this guy, a bit of trig.
Better make sure that's an integer.
And then again, here it's the same,
but for the column space.
So this is me just doing trig.
Okay.
And that's a bound on the rank.
It happens to be extremely good.
And if you work out what that rank is
and try to look back,
you'll find it's extremely efficient
to send the Japanese flag to your friend
in low rank form.
Because it's not full rank
because these numbers are so small.
So this comes out to be
like approximately a half R plus one.
So much smaller than what you would expect.
Because remember, a circle is almost
the anti version of aligned with the grid.
But yeah, it's still low rank.
Okay.
So, now, most matrices that we come up with
in computational math
are not exactly of finite rank.
They are of numerical rank.
And so I'll just define that.
So, the numerical rank of a matrix
is very similar to the rank,
except we allow ourselves
a little bit of wiggle room
when we define it.
Okay.
And so that amount of wiggle room
will be a parameter called toll,
called epsilon.
Okay.
That's a tolerance.
I'm thinking of epsilon as a tolerance.
That's the amount of wiggle room
I'm going to give myself.
Okay.
And we say that the numerical rank,
I'll put an epsilon there
to denote numerical rank,
is k.
If,
k is the first singular value,
or the last singular value above epsilon,
in the following sense,
I'm copying the definition above,
but with epsilons instead of zeros,
if this singular value
is less than epsilon,
relatively,
and the kth one was not below.
So, k plus one is the first singular value
below epsilon in this relative sense.
So,
so, of course,
the rank of zero, x,
if that was defined,
is the same as the rank of x.
Okay.
So this is just allowing ourselves some wiggle room.
But this is actually what we're interested more in in practice.
All right.
I don't want to necessarily send my friend the flag
to exact precision.
I would actually be happy to send my friend the flag
up to 16 digits of precision, for example.
They're not going to tell the difference between those two flags.
And if I can get away with compressing the matrix a lot more
once I have a little bit of wiggle room, that would be a good thing.
So we know from the ERCAC in Young
that the singular values tell us how well we can approximate x
by a low-rank matrix.
In particular, we know that the k plus 1 singular value of x
tells us how well x can be approximated by a rank k matrix.
For example, when the rank was exactly k,
the sigma k plus 1 was 0.
And then this came out to be 0,
and we found that x was exactly a rank k matrix.
Here, because we have the wiggle room, the epsilon,
we get an approximation, not an exact.
So this is telling us how well we can approximate x
by a rank k matrix.
That's what the singular values are telling us.
And so this allows us to try our best to compress matrices,
but use low-rank approximation rather than doing things exactly.
And of course, on a computer, when we're using floating-point arithmetic,
or on a computer because we always round numbers
to the nearest 16-digit number,
if epsilon was 16 digits,
your computer wouldn't be able to tell
that x is a rank k matrix.
So we can't tell the difference between x or x,
the rank k approximation,
if this number was satisfied this expression.
Your computer would think of x and xk as the same matrix
because it would inevitably round both to epsilon,
within epsilon.
So what kind of matrices are numerically of low rank?
Of course, all low-rank matrices are numerically of low rank,
because the wiggle room can only help you.
But it's far more than that.
There are many full-rank matrices,
matrices that don't have any singular values,
that are zero,
but the singular values decay rapidly to zero,
that are full-rank matrices with low numerical rank
because of the wiggle room.
So for example, here is the classic matrix
that fits this regime.
If I give you this, this is called the Hilbert matrix.
This is a matrix that happens to have,
extremely low numerical rank,
but is actually full-rank.
Which means that I can approximate h to,
by a rank k matrix where k is quite small,
very well, provided you give me some wiggle room.
But it's not a low-rank matrix in the sense
that if epsilon was zero here,
you didn't allow me the wiggle room,
all the singular values of this matrix are positive.
So it's of low rank,
it's of low numerical rank,
but not, it's not a low-rank matrix.
The other classical case, classic example,
which motivated a lot of the research in this area
was the Vandermonde matrix.
So here is the Vandermonde matrix.
An n by n version of it.
Think of the x i's as real.
This is Vandermonde.
This is the matrix that comes up when you try to do
polynomial interpolation at real points.
This is an extremely bad matrix to deal with
because it's numerically low-rank.
And often you actually want to solve
a linear system with this matrix.
And numerical low-rank,
it implies that it's extremely hard to invert.
So this is low-rank,
numerical low-rank is not always good for you.
Okay?
Often we want the inverse,
which exists.
But it's difficult because V is low.
It's very basic.
It's very many times more complicated,
because you do the binary formula
and then your qua-etin,
this chiarium, which is your q is less than 1,
gives you a solve.
What you would actually need to do is to,
B has low numerical rank.
Okay.
So people have been trying to understand
why these matrices are numerically of low rank
for a number of years.
And the classic reason
why there are so many low rank matrices
is because the world is smooth, as people say.
They say the world is smooth.
That's why matrices are of numerical low rank.
And to illustrate that point,
I will do an example.
So this is classically understood
by a man called Reed in 1983.
And this is what his reason was.
I have a picture of John Reed.
He's not very famous,
so I try to make sure his picture gets around.
He's playing the piano.
It's one of the only pictures I could find of him.
So what is in this reason?
Why do people say this?
Well, here's an example that illustrates it.
If I take a polynomial in two variables,
and I...
For example,
this is a polynomial of two variables,
and my x matrix comes from sampling
that polynomial integers,
for example,
this matrix,
then that matrix happens to be of low rank,
mathematically of low rank,
with epsilon equals zero.
Why?
Why is that?
Well, if I write down x as in terms of matrices,
you can easily see it.
So this is made up of a matrix of all ones
plus a matrix of j's.
So that's 1, 2, up to n.
1, 2, up to n.
Because every entry of that matrix
just depends on the row index.
And then this guy depends on both j and k.
So this...
This is a multiplication table, right?
So this is n, 2, 4, up to 2n,
n, 2n, n squared.
Okay.
Clearly, the matrix of all ones is a rank one matrix.
The same with this guy.
The column space is just of dimension one.
And this guy happens to...
The last guy also happens to be a matrix of all ones.
And this guy happens to be of rank one.
Because I can write this matrix in rank one form.
Which is a column vector times a row vector.
So this matrix x is of rank three.
I guess at most rank three is what I've actually shown.
Okay.
Now, of course, this isn't got to numerical low rank yet.
So let's get ourselves there.
So Reid knew this.
And he said to himself,
okay, well, if I can approximate...
If x is actually coming from sampling a function,
and I approximate that function by a polynomial,
then I'm going to get myself a low rank approximation
and get a bound on the numerical rank.
So...
So in general,
if I give you a polynomial of two variables,
which can be written down,
it's degree m in both x and y.
Let's say, keep these indexes away from the matrix index.
I give you this such a polynomial.
And I go away and I sample it.
And make a matrix x.
Then x, by looking at each term individually,
like I did there,
will have low rank mathematically
with epsilon equals zero.
This will have, at most, m squared rank.
And if m is three or four or ten,
it possibly could be low
because this x could be a large matrix.
Okay.
So what Reid did for the Hilbert matrix was said,
okay, well, look at that guy.
That guy looks like it's sampling a function.
It looks like it's sampling the function
one over x plus y minus one.
So he said to himself,
well, that x,
if I look at the Hilbert matrix,
then that is sampling a function.
It happens to not be a polynomial.
It happens to be this function.
But that's okay because sampling polynomials,
integers, gives me low rank exactly.
Maybe sampling smooth functions,
functions like this,
can be well approximated by polynomials
and therefore have low numerical rank.
And that's what he did in this case.
So here's, he did find,
he tried to find a p,
a polynomial approximation to f.
In particular, he looked at exactly this kind
of approximation.
So he has some numbers here that,
so that things get dissolved later.
But he tried to find a p that did this kind of approximation.
So this approximates f.
And then he would develop a low rank approximation to x
by sampling p.
So he would say, okay, well, one, two, three, four, five, six,
seven, eight, and so we've got the small tod and e,
and then he's drawing that go down.
And I'm Notge, and you know,
I can't just draw a little bit of the enumeration model,
and I'm 생각이, I can't just say,
no, it's this, everyday,
it becomes a Ahmed DC.
And he, he, you know,
he's looking forarrassed.
And I say I now need a grâce,
different of ilkwehса of course,
Same thing .
Okay?
Similarly,
so this,
like I .
I've got to a row.
Take hacerlo.
these factors were chosen just right.
The divide by n was chosen
so that the epsilon came out just there.
So for many years,
that was kind of the canonical reason
that people would give
that, well, if the matrix x
is sampled from a smooth function,
then we can approximate that function
by a polynomial
and get polynomial rank approximations,
and therefore the matrix x
will be of low numerical rank.
There's an issue with this reasoning,
especially for the Hilbert matrix,
that it doesn't actually work that well.
So, for example,
if I take the 1,000 by 1,000 Hilbert matrix
and I look at its rank,
okay, well, I've already told you
this is full rank.
You'll get 1,000.
All this.
All the singular values are positive.
If I look at the numerical rank
of this 1,000 by 1,000 Hilbert matrix
and I compute it,
I compute the SVD,
and I look at how many are above epsilon,
where epsilon is 10 to the minus 15.
So that means I can approximate
the 1,000 by 1,000 Hilbert matrix
by a rank 28 matrix
and only give up,
there will be an exact of 15 digits,
which is a huge amount.
So this is what we get in practice,
but Reed's argument here
shows that the rank of this matrix,
the numerical rank,
is at most,
equal to one word.
So it doesn't very good job
on the Hilbert matrix
for bounding the rank,
, all right.
So, Reed comes along,
takes this function
He tries to find a polynomial
that does this,
where epsilon is 10 to the minus 15.
He finds that he needs,
the number of turns that he needs
in this expression here
is around
719,
and therefore,
,
bound on the numerical rank.
The trouble is that 719
tells us that
this is not
of low numerical rank.
But we know it is.
So it's an unsatisfactory reason.
So
there's been
several people trying to come up
with more appropriate
reasons that explain
the 28 here.
And so
one reason that has
I've started to
use is that
another slightly different way of looking
at things, which is
to say the world
is Sylvester.
Now Sylvester
what does that mean? What does the word
Sylvester mean in this case?
It means that the matrices satisfy
a certain type of equation
called the Sylvester equation.
And
so the reason is really
many of these matrices
satisfy
a Sylvester equation
and that takes the form
for sum
A, B, and C.
So
X is your matrix of interest.
You want to show X's of numerical low rank.
And the task at hand is to find an A, B, and C
so that X satisfies that equation.
For example, all the matrices, the two matrices I've had on the board
satisfy a Sylvester equation.
A Sylvester matrix equation.
There is an A, a B, and a C
for which they do this.
For example,
remember that the matrix of the matrix is the matrix of the matrix.
Remember the Hilbert matrix,
which we have there still,
but I'll write it down again.
satisfies
has these entries.
So all we need to do is to try to figure out an A and B
and then a C
so that we can make it fit a Sylvester equation.
There's many different ways of doing this.
The one that I like
is the following.
What if I put a half here
and three over two here
all the way down here?
All the way down to n minus a half
times this matrix.
And I, so this is timesing the top of this matrix
by a half and then three over two
and then five over two.
So we're basically timesing that matrix,
each entry of this matrix by j minus a half.
And then I do something on the right of here,
which I'm allowed to do because I've got the B freedom.
And I choose this to be,
and I choose this to be the same up to a minus sign.
Then when you think about this,
what is it doing?
It's timesing the j k entry,
this is,
by j minus a half,
because that's what this is doing.
And what's this doing?
It's timesing the j k entry by k minus a half.
So this is, in total,
timesing the j k entry
by j plus k minus a half.
plus k minus 1 half minus 1 half, which is minus 1.
So this is timesing the jk entry by j plus k minus 1.
So it knocks out the denominator.
And what we get from this equation is a bunch of 1's.
So in this case, a and b are diagonal,
and c is the matrix of all 1's.
We can also do this for Vandermonde.
So Vandermonde, you'll remember, looks like this.
And then over here, we have this guy,
the matrix that appears with polynomial interpolation.
So if I think about this, I could
then also come up with an a, b, and c.
And for example, here's one that works.
I can stick the x's on the diagonal.
So this is, if you imagine what that matrix on the left
is doing, it's timesing each column by the vector x.
So the first column of this matrix becomes x, the vector x.
The second.
And the third becomes the vector x squared,
where squared is done entrywise.
And then the third entry is now x cubed.
And when we get to the last, it's x to the n.
So that's like multiplied each column by the vector x.
So if I want to try to come up with a matrix,
so what's left is of low rank.
It's like of this form.
What I can do is shift the columns.
So.
I've noticed.
That.
This.
Product.
Of this diagonal matrix has made the first column x.
So if I want to kill off that column,
I can take the second column and permute it to the first column.
I can take the third column and permute it to the second.
The last column, I permute it to the penultimate column here.
And that will actually kill off a lot of what I've created
in this matrix right here.
So let me write that down.
This is a circumshift matrix.
This does that permutation.
I've put a minus 1 there.
I could have put any number there.
Doesn't make any difference.
But this is the one that works out extremely nicely.
Now this zeroes out lots of things because of the way
I've done the multiplication by x and the circumshift
of the columns.
And so the first column is 0 because this first column is x.
This first column is x.
So I got x minus x.
This column.
So it was x squared minus x squared.
So I got 0.
And I just keep going along until that last column.
That last column is a problem because the last column
of this guy is x to the n, whereas I
don't have x to the n in v. So there's some numbers here.
You'll notice that c in both cases
happens to be a low-rank matrix.
In these cases, it happens to be of rank 1.
And so people were wondering, maybe it's something
to do with satisfying these kind of equations that
makes these matrices that appear in practice numerically
of low rank.
And after a lot of work in this area,
people have come up with a bound that
demonstrates that these kind of equations are key to understand,
meaning numerical low rank.
So if x satisfies a Sylvester equation like this, and a is normal, b is normal.
I don't really want to concentrate on that, those two conditions.
It's a.
It's a little bit academic.
Then people have found a bound on the singular values of any matrix that satisfies this kind
of expression.
And they found this following bound.
OK.
So here.
Here.
The rank of C is r.
So that goes there.
So in our case is the two examples we have r is 1.
So we can forget about r.
This nasty guy here is called the Zoeller-Terreff number.
E is a set that contains the eigenvalues of A.
It contains the eigenvalues of A.
And F is the set that contains the eigenvalues of B.
Okay.
Now, it looks like we have gained absolutely nothing by this bound,
because I've just told you singular values are bound by Zola-Tariff numbers.
That doesn't mean anything to anyone.
It means a little bit to me, but not that much.
So the key to this bound, the reason this is useful,
is that so many people have worked out what these Zola-Tariff numbers actually mean.
Okay.
So these are two key people that worked out what this bound means.
And we have gained a lot, because people have been studying this number.
This is like a number that people cared about from 1870 onwards to the present day.
And people have studied this.
And they've studied this number extremely well.
So we've gained something by turning it into a more abstract problem
that people have thought about previously.
And now we can go to the literature on Zola-Tariff numbers, whatever they are,
and discover this whole literature of work on this Zola-Tariff number.
And the key part, I'll just tell you the key,
is that the sets E and Z,
and F, are separated.
So, for example, in the Hilbert matrix,
the eigenvalues of A can be read off the diagonal.
What are they?
They are between minus a half and N minus a half.
And the eigenvalues of B lie in the set minus a half, minus N plus a half.
And the key reason why the Hilbert matrix is of low numerical rank
is the fact that these two sets are separated.
And that makes this Zola-Tariff number get small extremely quickly with K.
Now, you might wonder why there's a question mark on Penzel's name.
There's an unofficial curse that's been going on for a while.
Both these men died while working on the Zola-Tariff problem.
They both died at the age of 31.
One died by being hit by a train, Zola-Tariff.
It's unclear whether he was suicidal or was accidental.
Penzel died at the age of 31 in the Canadian mountains.
He was killed by an avalanche.
I am currently not yet 31, but going to be 31 very soon.
And I'm scared that I may join this list.
Okay.
But for the Hilbert matrix, what you get from this analysis,
based on these two people's work,
is a bound on the numerical rank.
And the rank that you get is, let's say,
a world record bound for the Hilbert matrix is 34.
Which is not quite 28.
Not yet.
But it's far more descriptive of 28 than 790.
And so this technique of bounding singular values
by using these Zola-Tariff numbers is starting to gain popularity
because we can finally, you know, get to the point where, you know,
we can finally, you know, get to the point where, you know,
we can finally answer to ourselves why there are
so many low-rank matrices that appear in computational math.
And it's all based on two 31-year-olds that died.
And so if you ever wonder when you're doing computational science
when a low rank appears and the smoothness argument does not work
for you, you might like to think about Zola-Tariff and the curse.
Okay.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Thank you, Ron.
Excellent.
How does it work now?
We're good.
Okay.
Yeah.
I'm happy to take questions if we have a minute,
if you have any questions.
How near 31 are you?
Why is there like a spotlight?
I'm 31 in December.
Wow.
So they died at the age of 31.
So, you know, next year is,
the scary year for me.
So I will be, yeah, not driving anywhere,
not leaving my house until I become 32.
Well, thank you all.
Okay.
Thanks.
.